<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Universal redemption offered in Jesus Christ in opposition to that pernicious and destructive doctrine of election and reprobation of persons from everlasting. By Jane Fearon.</title>
            <author>Fearon, Jane, 1654 or 5-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F576A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218275</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829884</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829884</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34331</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34331)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2029:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Universal redemption offered in Jesus Christ in opposition to that pernicious and destructive doctrine of election and reprobation of persons from everlasting. By Jane Fearon.</title>
                  <author>Fearon, Jane, 1654 or 5-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: "Universal redemption offered in Jesus Christ, &amp;c."; caption title on p. 6 reads: "Concerning the universality of God's love: and also the saving and spiritual light wherewith every man is lighted.".</note>
                  <note>Page 45 has caption title reading: Postscript: being remarks upon J.W.'s rhiming acrostick.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34331:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Redemption</hi> OFFERED IN JESUS CHRIST, In Oppoſition to That Pernicious and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Doctrine of ELECTION and REPROBATION of <hi>Perſons</hi> from <hi>Everlaſting.</hi> By <hi>JANE FEARON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For Zions ſake will I not hold my Peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake I will not reſt, until the Righteouſneſs thereof go forth as Brightneſs, and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof as a Lamp that burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. LXII. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:34331:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34331:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Redemption</hi> OFFERED IN JESUS CHRIST, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving for ſome time had an Unuſual Weight upon my Spirit, and many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deeply Exerciſed in Mind, I waited upon the <hi>LORD,</hi> that my Underſtanding might be clear in what he required of me, whoſe mighty Power reached unto my Soul, and by his Living Preſence my Heart was affected, and could ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to what the <hi>LORD</hi> required of me, becauſe of the Day of his Power, which otherways would have been a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34331:3"/>great Croſs to my own Will, which was to go to the Meeting of the People called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> at Great <hi>Broughtoun</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> where I ſtood for ſome time (till their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had done) waiting upon the <hi>LORD</hi> in much Trembling and Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of Soul and Spirit: And that which I had to Declare amongſt them (although not with <hi>Inticing Words of Mans Wiſdom,</hi> yet in <hi>the Demonſtration of the Spirit and Power,</hi> for my Heart was filled with the Love of <hi>GOD</hi> to ſuch whoſe Day of Viſitation was not Expired) was to ſhew unto them the great Benefit of the New Covenant which <hi>GOD</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifed to make with his People, as alſo the Univerſality of <hi>GOD</hi>'s Love to the Sons and Daughters of Men.</p>
            <p>But being oppoſed by <hi>Joſhua Ware</hi> (their Miniſter) was not ſuffered to Eaſe my Spirit, nor clear my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the ſight of <hi>GOD;</hi> but he ſpake with great Earneſtneſs, <hi>That none ſhould be ſuffered to ſpeak there,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34331:3"/>but who could give an Account of their Faith;</hi> and asked me, <hi>What I hoped to be ſaved by?</hi> To which I anſwered, <hi>Not by Works of Righteouſneſs that either I or any other could do, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of Regeneration, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral more Queſtions which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd to, which he could not by the Scripture contradict, in expectation I might have had liberty to clear my ſelf of the aforeſaid weight; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that, he with ſome others called to ſome to put me out, and ſaid, <hi>A Woman ſhould not be allowed to ſpeak;</hi> which matter I deſired often to ſpeak to, but could not be heard, they deſpiſing and rejecting the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I had to bear, altho in much love to their Souls, and the ſaid <hi>J. W.</hi> endeavoured to make it appear (by perverting the Scripture) that <hi>GOD</hi>'s Love was not to all, contrary to the Meſſage of the Angel, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. &amp; 10. And ſome of them ſaid, <hi>I preached
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34331:4"/>falſe Doctrine, in holding forth that Chriſt was a Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World.</hi> But with <hi>J. W.</hi> time after time, I offered a Publick <hi>Diſpute,</hi> and to maintain by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that <hi>Doctrine</hi> I did hold forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, but was denied, (as ſome Friends there with me can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) except on theſe terms, That only one Man of my Friends ſhould diſpute with him in my ſtead, and neither I nor any other ſhould be ſuffered to ſpeak a word: And unleſs I would promiſe not to ſpeak, I ſhould not be ſuffered to be where the <hi>Diſpute</hi> was; and that it ſhould be agreed upon that two Perſons ſhould be made choice of, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Diſpute (to be Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) neither of their Judgment not ours, to ſee that good Order was kept, and to Judge who is in the Right, and who in the Wrong; ſo it is evident the Moderators muſt have been of a different Faith and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from us Both. Now how this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34331:4"/>would conſiſt with true Chriſtianity, and a right Contending for the Faith delivered to the Saints, according to the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi>'s Advice, let it be ſeriouſly conſidered, for us to give up our Faith and Teſtimony, and to be concluded whether it's Right or Wrong, by Men not of the ſame Faith, we thought it very Improper, and that no true Chriſtian can do, and therefore could not anſwer his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals therein. And yet finding a Concern to remain upon my Mind, and ſo far as the <hi>LORD</hi> by his holy Spirit ſhall aſſiſt me, by bringing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Remembrance what may be ſuitable to the preſent Subject, ſhall bear Teſtimony to, in theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lines, in order to eaſe my Spirit and clear my Conſcience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34331:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of GOD's Love:</hi> AND ALSO The Saving and Spiritual LIGHT wherewith every Man is Lighted.</head>
            <p>GOD out of his Infinite Love, who delighteth not in the Death of a Sinner, but that all ſhould Live and be Saved, hath ſo loved the World, <hi>that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life,</hi> Joh. 3.16. And by his Light <hi>Lighteth every Man coming
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34331:5"/>into the World,</hi> John 1.9. Which Light maketh manifeſt all things that are <hi>reprovable,</hi> Epheſ. 5.13. And teacheth all Temperance, and Righteouſneſs, and Godlineſs, and this Light light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts of all Mankind, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Salvation of all, if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſted, nor is it leſs Univerſal than the Seed of Sin, being the Purchaſe of his Death who taſted Death for every Man; <hi>For as in Adam all died, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.22.</p>
            <p>As for that Doctrine, (viz. <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Reprobation</hi>) according to which ſome are not afraid to aſſert, <hi>That</hi> GOD <hi>by one Eternal and Immutable Decree, hath Predeſtinated to Eternal Damnation the far greater part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, without any reſpect to their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience or Sin, but only for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating the Glory of his Juſtice: And that for the bringing this about, he hath Appointed theſe Miſerable Souls, Neceſſarily to Walk in their Wicked Ways, that ſo his Juſtice may lay hold on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34331:6"/>them: And that GOD doth therefore not only ſuffer them to be liable to this Miſery in many Parts of the World, by with-holding from them the Preaching of the Goſpel and Knowledge of Chriſt; but even in thoſe Places where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is preached, and Salvation by Chriſt is offered, whom though he Publickly Invites them, yet he Juſtly Condemns them for Diſobedience; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath with-held from them all Grace, by which they could have laid hold on the Goſpel,</hi> viz. <hi>Becauſe he hath by a Secret Will unknown to all Men, Ordained and Decreed (without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had to their Diſobedience or Sin) that they ſhall not Obey, and that the Offer of the Goſpel ſhall never prove Effectual for their Salvation, but only ſerve to aggravate and occaſion their greater condemnation.</hi> I ſay, As to this horrible and blaſphemous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, our Cauſe is common with many Others, who have both Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Learnedly, according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Reaſon, and Antiquity, refuted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34331:6"/>it. Seeing then that ſo much is ſaid already againſt this Doctrine, that little can be added except what hath been already ſaid, I ſhall be ſhort; yet becauſe it lies ſo in oppoſition to my way, I cannot let it altogether paſs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is highly injurious to <hi>GOD,</hi> becauſe it makes Him the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Sin, which of all things is moſt contrary to His Nature: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Aſſerters of this Principle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this Conſequence, but that is but Mockery, ſeeing it ſo naturally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from their Doctrine, and is equally Ridiculous as if a Man ſhould obſtinately deny that One and Two makes Three: For if <hi>GOD</hi> has decreed the Reprobated ſhall Periſh, without all reſpect to their Evil Deeds, but only as his own Pleaſure; and if he hath alſo decreed, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were in being, or in any Capacity to do Good or Evil, that they ſhould walk in theſe Wicked
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34331:7"/>Ways, by which as a Secondary Means, they are led to that End; Who, I pray, is the Author and Cauſe thereof, but <hi>GOD,</hi> who ſo Willed and Decreed it? Is not this as Natural a Conſequence as can be?</p>
            <p>Secondly, This Doctrine is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to <hi>GOD,</hi> becauſe it makes Him appear to delight in the Death of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; yea, and will have many to die in their Sins: Contrary to theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. For if He hath created Men on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that End, that He might ſhew forth His Juſtice and Power in them, as ſome Affirm, and for effecting thereof hath not only with-held from them the Means of doing Good, but alſo fore-ordained the Evil that they ſhould fall into; muſt He not therefore delight in their Death, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt His own Will He neither doth nor can do any thing?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34331:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Is it not highly injurious to <hi>CHRIST</hi> our Mediator, and to the Efficacy and Excellency of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel? Does it not render his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ineffectual, as if he had not by his Sufferings throughly broken down the Middle Wall, nor yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd the Wrath of <hi>GOD,</hi> or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd the Love of <hi>GOD</hi> to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, if it was before decreed that it ſhould be of no Service to the far greater part of Mankind? It is to no purpoſe to alledge that the Death of <hi>CHRIST</hi> was Effectual enough to have ſaved all Mankind, if in effect its Vertue be not ſo far Extended as to put all Mankind in a capacity of Salvation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Makes it not the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel as a meer Mock and Deceit, if many of thoſe to whom it is Preached, be by an Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable Decree Excluded from being benefited by it? It wholly makes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34331:8"/>Uſeleſs the Preaching of Faith and Repentance, and the whole Tenor of the Goſpel-Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings (as being all Relative to a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Decree and Means before-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) to ſuch, which becauſe they cannot fail, Man needs do nothing but wait for that Irreſiſtable Snatch which will come, though it be but at the laſt hour of his Life, if he be in the Decree of Election: And be his Diligence and Waiting what it can, ſhall never Attain it, if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Decree of Reprobation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, This Doctrine is highly injurious to Mankind, and renders them in a far worſe Condition than the Devils in Hell; for they were ſometime in a capacity to have ſtood, and do ſuffer for their own Guilt: Whereas many Millions of Men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Doctrine, muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin, which they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew of, nor ever were acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to: It renders them worſe than
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34331:8"/>the Beaſts of the Field, of whom the Maſter requires no more than they are able to perform; and if they be kill'd, Death is to them an end of Sorrow; Whereas Man is for ever Tormented for not doing that which he was never able to do. It puts him in a far worſe condition than <hi>Pharoah</hi> put the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> for tho' he with-held Straw from them, yet by much Labour and Pains they could have gotten it. But from Men, they make <hi>GOD</hi> to with-hold all means of Salvation, ſo that by no means can they attain to it.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly removed this falſe Doctrine out of my way (which hath been a great Concern to me) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that are deſirous may ſee it Learnedly and Piouſly refuted by many others: I come to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Univerſal Redemption,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt's Dying for all Men,</hi> which is that Subject I find with me to Treat of, and is of it ſelf ſo Evident from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34331:9"/>the Scripture-Teſtimony, that there is ſcarce found any other Article of the Chriſtian Faith, ſo frequently, ſo plainly, and ſo poſitively Aſſerted: It is that which makes the Preaching of <hi>CHRIST</hi> to be truely termed the Goſpel, or the Meſſage of Glad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to all: Thus the Angel decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Birth and Coming of <hi>CHRIST</hi> to the Shepherds, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.10. <hi>Behold I bring you good Tydings of great Joy, which ſhall be to All People;</hi> he ſaith not to <hi>a Few People.</hi> Now if this Coming of <hi>CHRIST</hi> had not brought a poſſibility of Salvation to All, it ſhould rather have been Accounted Bad Tydings of great Sorrow to moſt People; Neither ſhould the Angel have had Reaſon to have ſung <hi>Peace on Earth, and Good Will towards Men,</hi> if the greateſt part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind had been neceſſarily ſhut out from Receiving any Benefit by it: How ſhould <hi>CHRIST</hi> have ſent out Diſciples to Preach the Goſpel to every Creature? <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. A very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34331:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>comprehenſive Commiſſion! That is, To every Son and Daughter of Mankind, without all Exception: He commands them to Preach Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all, Remiſſion of Sins to all, Warning every one, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting every one, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Col.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.28.</p>
            <p>Now how could they have Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpel to every Man, as became the Miniſters of <hi>JESUS CHRIST,</hi> in much Aſſurance of Salvation by that Goſpel, had it not been poſſible for all? What if ſome of us had asked, or ſhould now ask any of theſe who deny that <hi>CHRIST</hi> died for all, Hath <hi>CHRIST</hi> died for me? How can they with Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence give a certain Anſwer to this Queſtion? If they give a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Anſwer (as their Principle obligeth them to do) and ſay, <hi>If thou Repent, CHRIST died for thee;</hi> Doth not the ſame Queſtion ſtill recur, <hi>Hath CHRIST died for me,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34331:10"/>ſo as to make Repentance poſſible for me?</hi> To this they can Anſwer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, unleſs they run in a Circle.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Feet of thoſe that bring glad Tydings of the Goſpel of Peace, are ſaid to be <hi>Beautiful,</hi> for that they Preach the <hi>Common Solva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Repentance unto All,</hi> offering a Door of Mercy and Hope unto All, through <hi>JESUS CHRIST,</hi> who <hi>gave Himſelf a Ranſom for All.</hi> The Goſpel invites All, and certainly by the Goſpel, CHRIST intended not to deceive or delude the greater part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>If all then ought to look for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Him, He muſt needs have made Salvation poſſible to All: For who is bound to ſeek after that which is Impoſſible? Certainly it were a meer mocking of Men to bid them do ſo. And ſuch as deny that by the Death of Chriſt Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made poſſible unto all Men,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34331:10"/>do moſt Blaſphemouſly make <hi>GOD</hi> mock the World, in giving his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants a Commiſſion to Preach the Goſpel of Salvation unto All, while He hath before Decreed that it ſhould not be poſſible for them to Receive it; would not this make the LORD to ſend forth His Servants with a Lye in their Mouths, which were Blaſphemous to think, commanding them to bid all and every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that CHRIST died for them, and had purchaſed Life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whereas it is no ſuch thing, according to their afore mentioned Doctrine?</p>
            <p>But ſeeing CHRIST gave a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Preach Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins and Salvation to All, it is manifeſt he died for All: For he that hath Commiſſionated his Servants thus to Preach, is a <hi>GOD</hi> of Truth, and no Mocker of poor Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; neither doth he require of any Man that which is Impoſſible, but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34331:11"/>is a Principle of Truth Engraven in every Juſt Man's Mind: And ſeeing He is both a moſt Righteous and Merciful <hi>GOD,</hi> it cannot at all ſtand either with His Juſtice or Mercy, to bid ſuch Men Repent or Believe, to whom He has made it Impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Moreover, If we regard the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Scripture in this matter, where there is not one Scripture that I know of, that affirmeth CHRIST not to have died for All, there are divers that poſitively Aſſert He did, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>I exhort that firſt of all, Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks, be made for all Men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for this is good and Acceptable in the ſight of GOD our Saviour, who will have ALL MEN TO BE SAVED, and to come to the Knowledge of the Truth, who gave Himſelf a Ranſom FOR ALL, to be teſtified in due time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34331:11"/>
            <p>Except we will have the Apoſtle here to intend quite another thing than he aſſerted, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plain to confirm what we have here aſſerted; and this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth well Anſwer to that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Arguing which we have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto uſed: For firſt, The Apoſtle here exhorts him to <hi>Pray for All Men;</hi> and to withſtand ſuch an Objection, as if they had ſaid (with our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) CHRIST prayed not for the World, neither willeth He us to pray for All, becauſe He will not that All ſhould be Saved, but hath ordained many to be Damned, that He might ſhew forth His Juſtice in them: He withſtands, I ſay, ſuch an Objection, telling them, That <hi>it is good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of GOD, who will have ALL MEN TO BE SAVED.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire to know what can be more expreſly affirmed? Or can any two Propoſitions be ſtated in Terms more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34331:12"/>Contradictory than theſe Two, <hi>GOD willeth that Some Men ſhall Not be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; GOD willeth All Men to be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> or <hi>GOD will have No Man Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> If we believe the laſt, as the Apoſtle hath affirmed, the firſt muſt be deſtroyed; ſeeing of Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Propoſitions, the one being Placed, the other is Deſtroyed: Whence (to conclude) he gives us a Reaſon of His willingneſs that All Men ſhould be Saved, in theſe words, <hi>Who gave Himſelf A RANSOM FOR ALL:</hi> As if he would have ſaid, Since <hi>CHRIST</hi> died for All Men, ſince he gave Himſelf a Ranſom for All, therefore he would have All Men to be Saved.</p>
            <p>This CHRIST Himſelf gives as the Reaſon of <hi>GOD's</hi> Love to the World, in theſe Words, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>GOD ſo loved the World, that He gave His only begotten Son, that WHOSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EVER Believeth in Him ſhould not Periſh, but have Everlaſting Life;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34331:12"/>compared with <hi>John</hi> 4.9. This is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poſitively affirmed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. in in theſe words, <hi>But we ſee JESUS, who was made a little lower than the Angels, for the Suffering of Death; Crowned with Glory and Honour, that He by the Grace of GOD, SHOULD TASTE DEATH FOR EVERY MAN.</hi> He that will but open his Eyes, may ſee this Truth here aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; If he taſted Death for EVERY Man, then certainly there is NO Man for whom He did not taſte Death; then there is no Man who may not be made a Sharer of the Benefit of it: <hi>For He came not to Condemn the World, but that the World through Him might be Saved,</hi> John 3.17. <hi>He came not to Judge the World, but to Save the World,</hi> Joh. 12.47. If He never came to bring Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to great part of Mankind, but that his coming (though it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do them good, yet) ſhall augment their Condemnation: from thence it neceſſarily follows, that He came
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34331:13"/>not of Intention to Save, but to Judge and Condemn the greater part of the World, contrary to His own Expreſs Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>And as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in theſe words above-cited, doth aſſert <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively</hi> that <hi>GOD</hi> willeth the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>ALL;</hi> ſo doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> aſſert <hi>Negatively,</hi> that he <hi>Willeth Not</hi> the Periſhing of any, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>The LORD is not ſlack con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Promiſe, as ſome Men count ſlackneſs, but is long ſuffering to us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that All ſhould come to Repentance.</hi> And this is correſpondent to that of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap. 33.11. <hi>As I live, ſaith the LORD, I have no pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his Ways and live.</hi> If it be ſafe to believe <hi>GOD,</hi> and to truſt in him, we muſt not think he intends to cheat us by all theſe Expreſſions through his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; but that he was in good Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34331:13"/>And that this Will and Deſire of His, hath not taken effect, the blame is on our parts; which could not be, if ſo be we were never put in any capacity of Salvation, and that CHRIST had never died for us, but left us under an Impoſſibility of Salvation.</p>
            <p>What means all thoſe Earneſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations, all theſe Serious Expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, wherewith the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are full? As, <hi>Why will you die, O Houſe of Iſrael? Why will you not come unto me, that you might have Life? I have waited to be gracious unto you; I have ſought to gather you; I have knocked at the Door of your Hearts: Is not your Deſtruction of your ſelves? I have called all the Day long.</hi> If Men who are ſo Invited, be under no ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of being ſaved, if Salvation be impoſſible unto them, why doth the Pſalmiſt expreſs himſelf thus, <hi>The LORD is gracious and full of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, ſlow to anger, and of great
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34331:14"/>Kindneſs</hi> (or Mercy) <hi>The LORD is good to all, and his Tender Mercies are over all His Works;</hi> of which, Man is the Nobleſt Part.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine is abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>And if any Man ſin, we have an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the FATHER, JESUS CHRIST the Righteous, and He is the Propitiation for our Sins; and not for ours only, but alſo for the Sins of the WHOLE WORLD.</hi> Here the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>John</hi> tells us plainly, That CHRIST not only died for him, and for the Saints and Members of the Church of GOD to whom he wrote, but for the WHOLE WORLD. Let us then hold it for a Certain and Undoubted Truth, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as oppoſe.</p>
            <p>If we Regard the Teſtimony of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> we muſt conclude that the Death of CHRIST was as large to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34331:14"/>Save, as <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin was to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15, 18. where he ſays. <hi>For if through the Offence of One many be Dead, much more the Grace of GOD, and the Gift by Grace, which is by one Man, JESUS CHRIST: Therefore as by the Offence of One, Judgment came upon ALL MEN to Condemnation; EVEN SO by the Righteouſneſs of One the Free Gift came upon ALL MEN to Juſtification of Life.</hi> And we all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin brought the Curſe upon all his Poſterity: And ſhall we not, likewiſe believe that <hi>as in Adam ALL Die, ſo in CHRIST ſhall ALL be made Alive.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.22.</p>
            <p>This alſo might be proved from many other Scripture-Teſtimonies, if it were at this Seaſon needful; but the afore-mentioned Scriptures being ſo clear, except a Man will cloſe his Eyes, he cannot but ſee the Truth of this Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:34331:15"/>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, <hi>What is then the Cauſe of Condemnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> According to <hi>John</hi> 3. &amp; 18. <hi>He that believeth in Him is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; but he that believeth not, is condemned already, becauſe hath not believed on the Name of the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of GOD: And this is the Condemnation, that Light is come into the World, and Men love Darkneſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Light, becauſe their Deeds are evil: For every one that doth evil, hateth the Light, neither cometh to the Light, leſt his Deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved: But he that doth Truth cometh to the Light that his Deeds may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in GOD,</hi> John 3. &amp; 19, 20, 21. And CHRIST exhorted thoſe who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, <hi>while they had the Light to believe in the Light, that they might be the Children of the Light,</hi> John 12.36. Whereby it may be concluded that the Light, Grace, or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34331:15"/>Meaſure of GOD's Spirit, may be Removed from them, which ſtrives with a Man in order to ſave him, during the time of his Viſitation, which GOD gives unto All, in which Time or Day they may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>We do not underſtand the whole Time of every Mans Life, though to ſome it may be extended even to the very hour of their Death, as we ſee in the Example of the Thief up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs. But ſuch a Seaſon at leaſt, as ſufficiently cleareth GOD of every Man's Condemnation, which may be to ſome ſooner, and to ſome later, according as the LORD in His Wiſdom ſees meet; ſo that many Men may out-live this Day; after which there may be no poſſibility of Salvation to them; and GOD juſtly ſuffers them to be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, as a juſt Puniſhment of their Unbelief; and even raiſes them up as Inſtruments of Wrath, and makes them a Scourge one againſt another.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34331:16"/>Whence to Men this Condition may be fitly applied thoſe Scriptures ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. from Verſ. 17. to the end; but eſpecially Verſ. 28. <hi>Even as they did not like to retain GOD in their Knowledge, GOD gave them up to a Reprobate Mind, to do thoſe things that are not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That many may out-live this day of GOD's gracious Viſitation to them, is ſhewn by Example of <hi>Eſau, Heb.</hi> 12.16, 17. who ſold his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, ſo he had it once, and was capable to have kept it; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when he would have Inherited the Bleſſing he was rejected.</p>
            <p>This appears alſo by CHRIST's weeping over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Luk. 19.42. ſaying, <hi>If thou hadſt known IN THIS THY DAY, the things that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Peace; BUT NOW they are hid from thine Eyes;</hi> which plainly imports a Time when they might
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34331:16"/>have known them, which was now removed from them, though they were yet alive.</p>
            <p>Therefore we having the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Inward and Powerful Work of this Light in our Hearts, even CHRIST revealed in us, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe to proclaim the Day of the LORD that is Ariſen in it, crying out with the Woman of <hi>Samaria, Come and ſee one that hath told me all that ever I have done; Is not this the CHRIST?</hi> That others may come and feel the ſame in themſelves, and may know that little ſmall thing that reproves them in their Hearts, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have neglected it, is no leſs than the Goſpel preached in them, <hi>CHRIST the Wiſdom and Power of GOD,</hi> being thereby ſeeking to ſave their Souls.</p>
            <p>This is that Univerſal Evangelical Principle, in and by which this Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34331:17"/>of CHRIST is ſhewn or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to all Men, both Jew and Gentile, Barbarian and <hi>Scythian,</hi> of whatſoever Countrey he be. And therefore <hi>GOD</hi> hath raiſed up unto Himſelf, in this our Age, Faithful Witneſſes and Evangeliſts, to preach again His Everlaſting Goſpel, and to direct as well the high Profeſſors, who boaſt of the Scriptures, and the outward knowledge of CHRIST, as the Infidels and Heathens that know Him not, that way; that they may all come to mind the Light in them, and know <hi>CHRIST</hi> in them the Juſt One, whom they had ſo long killed and made merry over, and He hath not reſiſted, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.6. And give up their Sins, Iniquities, Falſe Faiths, Profeſſions, and Out-ſide Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to be Crucify'd by the Power of his Croſs (or Spirit) in them, ſo as they may know CHRIST Within to be the Hope of Glory; and may come to walk in his Light,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34331:17"/>and to be ſaved, <hi>Who is that True Light that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having briefly hinted concerning the Univerſal Redemption by <hi>CHRIST,</hi> which for ſome Time hath been a Concern upon my Mind, I ſhall proceed to ſpeak ſomething in ſhort concerning the New Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, The Days come, ſaith the LORD, that I will make a New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Houſe of Iſrael, and with the Houſe of Judah; not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Covenant which I made with their Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaith the LORD, I will put my Law in their Inward Parts, and write it in their Hearts, and will be their GOD, and they ſhall be my People: And they ſhall teach no more every Man his Neighbour,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34331:18"/>and every Man his Rrother, ſaying, Know the LORD; for they ſhall all know Me, from the leaſt of them to the greateſt: For I will forgive their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and I will remember their Sins no more,</hi> Jer. 31.31, 32, 33, 34.</p>
            <p>Now thoſe that would have this great Benefit, to be GOD's People, and to have this great Bleſſing of the Goſpel, to have their Iniquities For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and would know the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his holy Spirit, muſt take heed to this Law written in the Heart: So ſhall ſuch witneſs with the Apoſtle, That GOD having rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up his Son <hi>JESUS,</hi> (whom he hath given for a Light to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and for a Covenant to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) and ſent him to bleſs them, in turning away every one of them from their Iniquities; otherways ſuch Deprive Themſelves of that Good the LORD intended for them, as may be ſeen in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 18. &amp; 9.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34331:18"/>where it is ſaid, <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Kingdom, to Build and to Plant it; if it do Evil in my Sight, that it obey not my Voice, then I will repent of the Good wherewith I ſaid I would Benefit them.</hi> As alſo in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 55. verſ. 7. where it is ſaid, <hi>Let the Wicked forſake his way, and the Unrighteous Man his Thoughts; and let him return unto the LORD, and he will have Mercy upon him; and to our GOD, and He will abundantly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Whereby it may be plainly underſtood, although the Covenant be ſure on <hi>GOD</hi>'s Part, yet the Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure is on Mans Part, in not Abiding in this holy Covenant, and in diſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding and ſlighting that Law (or Light) <hi>GOD</hi> hath appointed for a Teacher, for a Guide, and for a Leader, which would lead into all Truth, Holineſs and Purity, without which <hi>No Acceptance with GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:34331:19"/>
            <p>And furthermore, The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Excellency of this Law, ſaith, <hi>The Law of the Spirit of Life in CHRIST JESUS, hath made me free from the Law of Sin and Death: For what the Law could not do, in that it was weak through the Fleſh, GOD ſending His own SON in the likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and for Sin, condemned Sin in the Fleſh, that the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as he delighted in the Law of GOD after the Inward Man, and could ſpeak of the Efficacy of it, and the Sufficiency thereof, ſo it may be obſerved the great Benefit he received, through minding this Law, and believing in it, was, that it ſet him free from the Law of Sin and Death; it was that whereby he was tranſlated out of the Power and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34331:19"/>Kingdom of Satan, into the Power and Kingdom of the Dear SON of GOD, who is ſufficient for all that believe on him: <hi>For</hi> GOD <hi>ſent not his SON into the World to condemn the World, but that the World through Him might be ſaved,</hi> John 3.17. as they believe on Him: Otherways, according to his own Saying, <hi>If ye believe not that I am He, ye ſhall die in your Sins; and whither I go, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye cannot come,</hi> John 12.46, 47. Who ſaith again, <hi>And if any Man hear my Words, and believe not, I Judge him not; for I came not to Judge the World, but to Save the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it appears that the Love of GOD is held out to All, that All might have been, or may be ſaved by <hi>CHRIST.</hi> But alas! it proved the miſery of the Jews, who were of that Stock of whom <hi>CHRIST</hi> came, according to the Fleſh (GOD's Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People) whom he had choſen
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34331:20"/>above all the Families of the Earth, to fall ſhort through Unbelief; and becauſe they Believed Him not, they did not Receive Him; but they that Believed Him, Received Him: <hi>And as many as Received Him, to them He gave Power to become the Sons of GOD,</hi> John 1.12, 13.</p>
            <p>So here may be plainly ſeen, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief was the Cauſe wherefore the Jews came ſhort of the Benefit that GOD is beſtowing upon ſuch who do not only believe that <hi>CHRIST</hi> our <hi>LORD</hi> came in that prepared Body to do the Will of His <hi>FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER,</hi> to be offered up once for all; but alſo believing on Him, as He is come the ſecond time without Sin unto Salvation; waiting for His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Appearance by His Light and Grace in their Hearts and Souls, that thereby they may know the Great Work of Regeneration, with out which they cannot ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34331:20"/>of GOD, nor doubtleſs enter into it. So it may be obſerved the Fault is on Mans Part, and not by an Eternal and Abſolute Decree, as ſome aſſert.</p>
            <p>Again, It is ſaid in <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. &amp; 20. <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the Door and Knock; IF ANT MAN hear my Voice, and open the Door, I will come in and ſup with him, and he with Me.</hi> And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that hearken to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking Voice of the Son of GOD, who is Undoubtedly knocking at the Door of every Mans heart, during the day of his Viſitation, in order to reclaim him from the Evil of his ways, and to cleanſe his Heart from all Iniquity, that ſo he may be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or Married to the Lamb. But and if Man will not hear His Voice, nor hearken, the <hi>LORD</hi> will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be clear of his Blood, and his Deſtruction will be upon his own Head.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34331:21"/>
            <p>And again, It may be read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. &amp; 17. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride faith Come, and let him that heareth ſay Come, and let him that is athirſt Come, and WHOSOEVER will, let him take of the Water of Life freely;</hi> Mark, <hi>WHOSOEVER,</hi> ſo there is None Excluded: And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of our LORD, <hi>John</hi> 4. &amp; 14. <hi>But WHOSOEVER drinketh of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never Thirſt; but the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I ſhall give him ſhall be in him a Well of Water ſpringing up unto Everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the Benefit of it, and the Joy of it unto ſuch who know the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up thereof, is that which cannot be Demonſtrated, as it is Felt and Witneſſed! There is much Aſſurance of Peace! It ſprings up to Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life! There's no Thirſting after any other Refreſhment to the Soul,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34331:21"/>but that which proceeds from the Spirit; <hi>For this ſpake He of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſuch ſhould receive who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on Him.</hi> O what pity it is that poor Mankind ſhould deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of ſuch Great Bleſſings, ſuch Unutterable Kindneſs, ſuch Great Favour, ſuch Joy, as to draw Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of the Well of Salvation in themſelves, by falling ſhort through Unbelief, as did the Jews! <hi>For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Unbelief they were broken off. Behold therefore the Goodneſs and Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of GOD! On them which fell, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity; but towards thee Goodneſs, if thou continue in his Goodneſs, otherwiſe thou ſhalt alſo be cut off, Rom.</hi> 11.22.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel; it is the Power of GOD unto Salvation, unto every one that believeth:</hi> But he that believeth not, excludes himſelf from the Benefit of this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Power.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:34331:22"/>
            <p>Moreover it is ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. &amp; 20. <hi>Wiſdom crieth without, ſhe uttereth her Voice in the Streets, ſhe crieth in the chief Places of Concourſe, in the openings of the Gates, in the City ſhe uttereth her Words, ſaying, How long, ye Simple ones, will ye love Simplicity, and the Scorners delight in their ſcorning, and Fools hate Knowledge? Turn you at my Reproof; Behold, I will pour out my Spirit unto you, I will make known my words unto you: Becauſe I have called and ye refuſed, I have ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out my Hand, and no Man regarded; but ye have ſet at nought all my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and would have none of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, I alſo will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your fear cometh.</hi> Here may be ſeen the Love of GOD with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of Perſons, when He is calling to the Scorners, to the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to Fools: As likewiſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34. where the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Of a Truth I perceive that GOD is no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34331:22"/>Reſpecter of Perſons, but in every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he that feareth Him and worketh Righteouſneſs, is Accepted with Him:</hi> So he makes the <hi>Fear of GOD,</hi> and the <hi>working of Righteouſneſs,</hi> the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications.</p>
            <p>Such then that have this, are Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, where-ever they be; <hi>But Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and Anguiſh upon every Soul of Man that doth Evil, to the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Gentile, for there's no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons with GOD;</hi> where the Apoſtle clearly ſhews, concerning Jew and Gentile, they that have an outward Law, and they that have none, when they do Good ſhall be Juſtified, and partake of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Glory and Peace, which comes upon every one that doth Good: And in <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. and 6, 7. where the LORD expreſſeth himſelf unto <hi>Cain</hi> thus, <hi>And the LORD ſaid unto Cain, Why art thou wroth, and why is thy Countenance fallen? If thou doeſt well,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34331:23"/>ſhalt thou not be Accepted? And if thou doeſt not well, Sin lieth at thy Door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here again it may be obſerved, It is in the Well-doing the Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is, and not by an Eternal and Abſolute Decree, as aforeſaid: Had not <hi>Cain</hi> a Day of Viſitation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him of GOD? And was it not poſſible in that day, even for <hi>Cain,</hi> to be Accepted? Otherwiſe would GOD have propoſed the doing Good as a Condition, if He had not given <hi>Cain</hi> ſufficient Strength, whereby he was capable to do Good?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That there is a Day of Viſitation given to the Wicked, wherein they might have been Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and that being Expired, they are ſhut out from Salvation; Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears evidently by CHRIST's La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over <hi>Jeruſalem: And when he was come near, he beheld the City,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34331:23"/>and wept over it, ſaying, If thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy Day, the things that belong to thy Peace! But now they are hid from thine Eyes.</hi> What can be more evinent, than that there was a Day wherein the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> might have known thoſe things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to their Peace; and that during that Day, He was willing to have gathered them, even as a Hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her Chickens; but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and therefore the Things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their Peace, were hid from their Eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Whereas they ſay, <hi>That GOD hath fore-ordained</hi> WHATSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EVER COMES TO PASS: It's a Contradiction to that Scripture where the LORD ſaid—<hi>And they have built the High Places of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, which is in the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, to burn their Sons and and their Daughters in the Fire, which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34331:24"/>I Commanded them not, NEITHER CAME IT INTO MY HEART,</hi> Jer. 7.31.—Here it is plain, GOD never Ordained the Burning of their Children, yet it came to paſs.</p>
            <p>Again, If a certain Number be decreed for Heaven, and another cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Number for Hell, CHRIST, his Prophets and Apoſtles never added one by all He and they did or could do; and much leſs can the Preachers of ſuch Doctrine add any; therefore it is not juſt to receive Wages from ſuch as they add nothing unto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:34331:24"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT: BEING REMARKS upon <hi>J.W.</hi>'s RHIMING ACROSTICK.</head>
            <p>HAving lately ſeen a Paper written Alphabetically by way of Poem, with an Acro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick of <hi>Joſhua War</hi>'s Name, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhews the Reader his Opinion in ſome Divinity (as he calls it) which he cannot truly ſay, except he be Divinely inſpired, becauſe the word imports the Myſtery of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Things, which muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from immediate Revelation. Likewiſe in the ſame Acroſtick he ſays,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34331:25"/>
               <hi>Above all Human Arts I here have writ;</hi> If above all human Arts, what muſt it proceed from, leſs than the Spirit of <hi>GOD?</hi> (without which no Man knows the things of <hi>GOD,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle.) And if ſo, let the Reader judge whether it be not from the Revealed Mind of GOD within, yea or nay, which heretofore hath been denied by them, whom now he appears to be a Paſtor to.</p>
            <p>He begins his Alphabet with ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> as <hi>GOD</hi> created him in a ſtate of Happineſs, free from Sin: It is certainly belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved GOD did place <hi>Adam</hi> in this happy ſtate in his own Image of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Purity, that he ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie Him above the reſt of His Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, all which do ſhew forth the Glory of <hi>GOD,</hi> and declare his handy work: But how much more Man, the Nobleſt part thereof, created in Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Uprightneſs; and while he did there abide, was in a Capacity to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34331:25"/>Anſwer the Mind of GOD, and was well-pleaſing to GOD, and good in His ſight; for if all the reſt of the Creation was Good, ſurely Man the Nobleſt Part thereof was Good, who above all the Creation was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in the Image of GOD: But all the Creation was Good, therefore Man was Good: Then how will it be proved that from Eternity <hi>Adam</hi> was Reprobated, or by the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or will of GOD <hi>Adam</hi> fell, as <hi>J. W.</hi> would make it appear; thoſe that are ſaved, GOD in Eternity deſigned to ſave; ſo thoſe that are Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it will follow, was in Eternity ſo deſigned? Likewiſe how then do his following words conſiſt with this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, where he ſays, <hi>Condemned he was WHEN he did thus offend, and in him his whole Poſterity:</hi> If it was <hi>when</hi> he did offend, then not from Eternity; <hi>But it was WHEN he did offend,</hi> ſays <hi>J.W.</hi> and therefore not from Eternity. <hi>J.W.</hi> is in this part of our Judgment. At the Letter <hi>F.</hi> he ſays,</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:34331:26"/>
            <q>
               <p>From this fearful ſtate of Sin &amp; Miſery, GOD hath found out for thoſe that are undone,</p>
               <p>From Law and Sin to work Delivery, By JESUS CHRIST, His Well-Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I Anſwer, We are of his Judgment in this part, That our <hi>LORD JESUS CHRIST</hi> laid down his Life for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that He might free them from the afore-mentioned ſtate, according to that Saying, <hi>And thou ſhalt call His Name JESUS, for he ſhall Save His People from their Sins:</hi> And that of <hi>John, Behold the Lamb of GOD which taketh away the Sins of the World,</hi> Joh. 1.29. And if there can be any Man found who was not of this Number, <hi>viz.</hi> Sinners, <hi>CHRIST</hi> hath not died for all: but there can be no Man found who was not of this Number, Therefore <hi>CHRIST</hi> died for all. So <hi>JW.</hi> is in this Verſe alſo of our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that <hi>CHRIST</hi> died for all, ſince all are undone by Sin.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34331:26"/>
            <p>But in his Next, he is quite of another Mind, when he ſays, (in contradiction to what he writ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) <hi>GOD in Eternity deſigned to ſave a certain Number in his Son, and all of them he gave unto him, who (then) by Him were freed from Wrath to come: (Then)</hi> to wit, from Eternity. Here he is for a certain Number, and the reſt to remain in that fearful ſtate before-mentioned; as if GOD nor CHRIST ever purpoſed Love nor Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to a great part of Mankind, and that the Coming and Sufferings of CHRIST never was intended, nor could be uſeful to their Juſtification, becauſe when he ſpeaks of the ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtrange cries he ſent up to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>when He the Sins of the Elect did bear;</hi> when the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2. <hi>And if any Man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, even JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST the Righteous: And He was the Propitiation for our Sins; and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the WHOLE WORLD:</hi> And if for the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34331:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Whole World,</hi> not only for the Sins of the Elect. The way which ſome take to avoid this Teſtimony, is moſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and ridiculous; <hi>The World here,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is the World of Believers:</hi> For this Commentary they have nothing but their own Aſſertion, and ſo while it manifeſtly deſtroys the Text, may be juſtly rejected: And if <hi>J.W.</hi> be in this Mind, as I ſuppoſe he is by what I heard him ſpeak, let him ſhew me, if he can, in all the Scripture, where the <hi>whole World</hi> is taken for Believers only. But I ſhall ſhew him where it is taken for quite the contrary; as, <hi>The World knows Me not, the World receives Me not, I am not of this World;</hi> beſides many other Scriptures, as, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.7, 8.26.12, 19.14.17.15.18, 19. 17 15, 18, 16.17.24.18. and many more: Secondly, The Apoſtle in this very place diſtinguiſheth the <hi>World</hi> from the <hi>Saints</hi> thus, <hi>And not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World;</hi> What means the Apoſtle here by <hi>ours?</hi> Is not that the Sins of Believers? Was
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34331:27"/>he not one of thoſe Believers? And was not this an Univerſal Epiſtle, written to all the Saints, that then were ſo, except he can make it appear the Apoſtle meant another thing than he ſpoke, <hi>CHRIST is the Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Run Sinners then to CHRIST without Delay:</hi> If they belong to the Decree of Reprobation, what will it avail them to run? What will avail their Prayers, Cries or Tears, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for their Souls, or walking hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in <hi>GOD</hi>'s ſight? According to that deſtructive Doctrine, they may as well ſit ſtill, and do nothing. Would not this Doctrine give way to all Looſeneſs and Profanity? For if it was decreed from Eternity they were of the Elect, there is no regard to Works, Good or Bad; contrary to that Scripture where it's ſaid, <hi>Behold I come quickly, and my Reward is with me, to give to every Man according as his Works ſhall be.</hi> I am not ſpeaking of Works wrought in our own fallen
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34331:28"/>Nature, which we by our own ſtrength have wrought, our own Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Performances, and therefore may be truly and properly called ours, whatever ſpecious Appearances they may ſeem to have, but by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Regeneration, and renewing of the <hi>Holy GHOST,</hi> ſeeing Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Work comprehenſive of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Works, even of all thoſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Fruits of the SPIRIT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth he not contradict Himſelf, when he ſaith, <hi>The worſt of Sinners, they may be welcome to JESUS; on him their Souls to reſt,</hi> when before he was but for a certain Number? If he, or any of his Opinion, can groundedly tell that they are of that Elect Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that CHRIST hath died for, if they be ſuch as belong to the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grace, otherwiſe they may as well ſit ſtill and do nothing. So one while this, another while that, ſuch mingled Doctrine! But how ſhould it be otherwiſe, when there's ſo little Zeal for GOD, among thoſe he calls
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34331:28"/>his own People, as he confeſſes in his laſt Verſe? But <hi>CHRIT</hi> tells us what's the cauſe, <hi>When Iniquity ſhall abound, the Love of many ſhall wax cold:</hi> When love to ſomething elſe gets more room in the Heart than the <hi>LORD JESUS,</hi> ſuch render themſelves unworthy of Him, according to His own Saying, <hi>He that loves Father or Mother, Wife or Children,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>more than Me, is not worthy of Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I have before written, is not out of a Prejudiced Mind, or the leaſt Tincture of Enmity or Hatred to the Perſons of any, neither durſt I forbear for the fear of procuring the Ill Will or Hatred of any: <hi>For GOD hath not given us the Spirit of Fear, but of Love and of a ſound Mind,</hi> who is my Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who knows it's all my deſire that <hi>Zion may ſhine, and Jeruſalem may become the Praiſe of the whole Earth, and that GOD would enlarge the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his Sanctuary, and his Dominion may be from Sea to Sea, and many may
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34331:29"/>be the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem,</hi> the very Entrance into whoſe Gates are Praiſes, and Bleſſed are they that do His Commandments (which and not Grievous but Joyous.) And ſuch <hi>have Right to the Tree of Life, and enters in through the Gates into the City, the New Jeruſalem, where Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, Honour and Glory, with Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Obedience, is Returned to Him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb, for ever and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>the 26th of the firſt Month, 1698.</date> 
               <hi>I am a Well-Wiſher to the Souls of all People,</hi>
               <signed>JANE FEARON</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34331:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
